Finding Aid of the UW-Milwaukee Dept. of English Records, 1945-2008
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
UW-Milwaukee Dept. of English Records, 1945-2008
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee. Dept. of English
UWM Archival Collection 127
Accession 2010-037
4.6 cubic ft. (4 boxes) plus additions of 6 cubic ft. (6 boxes)
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
Collection documents much of the routine administrative operations of the UW-Milwaukee Dept. of English mainly from 1959 to 1979. Included are various committee files and on-campus correspondence documenting curriculum planning, staffing and budgeting. Correspondence is largely on-campus. Pre-1956 records were created by the English Department chair of the Wisconsin State College, Milwaukee, and concern the merger with the University of Wisconsin Extension and routine administrative affairs.
In 1927, when the Normal School became the Milwaukee State Teacher's College, English was incorporated into the program leading to a four year Bachelor's of Education degree. English itself was offered as a Bachelor of Arts degree when the transition into Wisconsin State College occured in 1951. In 1956, following the merger of Wisconsin State College and the University of Wisconsin Extension, the English Department became part of the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee College of Letters & Science, where it continued as a bachelor's program. In 1962, the department added two graduate degrees--either an M.A. in English or an M.S. which combined English and education. Beginning in 1967, a Ph.D was also offered by the department.
Department Chairs
1956-1959 Max Freeman
1959-1961 Ralph Aderman
1961-1964 Edward D. Holst
1964-1967 Gareth W. Dunleavy
1967-1970 Robert K. Turner
1970-1973 Justin Replogle
1973-1976 Kathryn Whitford
1976-1979 Donald Emerson
1979-1982 Thomas Bontly
1982-1985 James Kuist
1985-1989 James Sappenfield
1990-1994 Jane B. Nardin
1994-1998 James A. Sappenfield
1998-2001 Michael Noonan
2001-2002 James A. Sappenfield
2002-2005 Alice Gillam
2005-2010 Andrew Martin
2010-2014 Liam Callanan
2014- Mark Netzloff
This collection contains mostly documents from various programs within the department as well as meetings minutes from the executive committee, departmental committee, and some subcommittees. Of note are the records on the Milton Tercentenary Conference, held on the 300th anniversary of the poet's death to commemorate his works, which contain 27 audio reels, correspondence, and conference paraphenalia. The collection also contains subject files dealing with the Cheshire literary magazine, as well as files related to a 1960 radio series entitled "The Poet Views the World." Also included are records of Project Destiny, a 1960s program which introduced impoverished public school students to a university setting.
This collection was received in, and is organized in, multiple parts. Additional materials have not been physically or intellectually arranged and interfiled, and researchers may need to consult more than one part of the collection to locate similar materials.
UWM Archival Collection 127: Records, 1945-1989
The collection contains one additional accession.
Accession 2010-037: Syllabi, 1994-2008
The files are organized alphabetically by subject, then chronologically.
Related Material in the UWM Libraries
Milton Society of America Records UWM Manuscript Collection 104
UW-Milwaukee College of Letters & Science Records UWM Archival Collection 1
UW-Milwaukee Dept. of Classics Records UWM Archival Collection 22
UW-Milwaukee Dept. of English and Comparative Literature Records UWM Archival Collection 40
Cream City Review Records UWM Archival Collection 225
James Liddy Papers UWM Manuscript Collection 300
Administrative/Restriction Information
There are no access restrictions on the materials, and the collection is open to all members of the public in accordance with state law.
An unknown individual transferred the collection to the Archives prior to 1989. The Department of English donated additional materials in February 2011 (accession 2010-037).
Contents List
- Records, 1945-1989, UWM Archival Collection 127; 4.6 cubic ft. (4 boxes)
  - Afro-American Program, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Civilization Committee, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Articulated Instructional Media Program, Brochures/Pamphlets, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brochures and Information Sheets, 1962-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cheshire Literary Magazine, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - College Level Examination Program, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Committee on Regional Activity and Development, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1974 (Box 1, Folder 8-16)
  - Curriculum Committee, 1954-1969 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Departmental Bibliographer Records
    - Departmental Library Committee, 1962-1970 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Files, 1957-1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Library Report, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Ruth Mary Fox Fund, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Departmental By-Laws and Policies, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Departmental Committee, 1957-1981 (Box 1, Folder 23-33)
  - English Composition Program Coordinator
    - Remedial English, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Testing, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Writing Lab, 1971-1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - English Graduate Programs, 1969-1971, 1974-1977, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - English Institute, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee, 1956-1983 (Box 2, Folder 6-18)
  - Five Year Review
    - 1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - 1986 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Freshman Course Committee, 1956-1965 (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
  - Freshman English, 1956-1966 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Freshman English News, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Graduate Faculty, 1959-1972 (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
  - Graduate Policy, 1973-1984 (Box 3, Folder 8-13)
  - Graduate Policy Committee Meetings, 1979-1988 (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
  - Handbook, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Honors Program, 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Irish Studies
    - Membership List and Yeats Exhibit, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Newsletter, 1971-1978 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Joint Control Committee, 1957-1963 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Library Committee, 1957-1965 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Linguistics Workshop, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Load Reduction Committee, 1973-1976 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Meetings and Memos, 1954-1968 (Box 3, Folder 24-26)
  - Memos, 1956-1983 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Milton Tercentenary Conference
    - Audio
      - Charles Mann, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 5, Audio 1)
      - Gerald Stacey and Wolfgang Rudat, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 5, Audio 2)
      - Robert T. Fallon and Mortimer Frank, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 5, Audio 3)
      - William A. Oram and Barry Wind, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 5, Audio 4)
      - James Campbell and Gert Schiff, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 5, Audio 5)
      - Stella Revard-Baum and C.A. Patrides, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 5, Audio 6)
      - D.M. Harralson and R.G. Schoen, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 5, Audio 7)
      - Richard S. Ide and James Stephens, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 5, Audio 8)
      - John F. Huntley and M.F. McCanles, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 5, Audio 9)
      - John Mulder and Roger Rollin, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 6, Audio 10)
      - Sister Mason and James H. Sims, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 6, Audio 11)
      - V.R. Mollencott and John A. Via, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 6, Audio 12)
      - T. Kranidas and T. O'Keeffe, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 6, Audio 13)
      - C.J. Summers and James J. Egan, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 6, Audio 14)
      - M. Mikolajczak and William Hunter, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 6, Audio 15)
      - John Shawcross and R.F. Fleissner, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 6, Audio 16)
      - Florence Walzl and J. Max Patrick, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 6, Audio 17)
      - Sidney Warhaft and Ted Pebworth, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 6, Audio 18)
      - S.S. Stollman and R.C. Flannagan, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 7, Audio 19)
      - James G. Mengert and Thomas W. Hayes, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 7, Audio 20)
      - E.R. Gregory and Desmond Hamlet, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 7, Audio 21)
      - Rabbi J. Goldman and Roger H. Sundell, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 7, Audio 22)
      - Michael Lieb Symposium, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 7, Audio 23)
      - Barry Wind and Thomas Hayes, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 7, Audio 24)
      - E.R. Gregory and J. Max Patrick, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 7, Audio 25)
      - James Sims and John Shawcross, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 7, Audio 26)
      - Roger Sundell and A. Chambers, 1974, Audio reel (¼ in., 3 ¾ ips) (Box 7, Audio 27)
    - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Participant Handouts and Bibliographies, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Programs and Event Lists, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Milwaukee Studies in Language, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - NDEA Institute
    - Administration, Reports, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Press Releases, Clippings, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Newsletter, 1961-1974 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Planning Documents, 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Poet Views the World," English Department Radio Series, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Poetry Center Proposal, 1963-1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Project Destiny
    - Correspondence, 1964-1969 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Description, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Photographs, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Press Releases, Newsclippings, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Publicity, Pamphlets, 1964-1968 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Reports, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Proposals, PhD and M.A. Program, 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Publications, English Usage Handbook, 1945-1960 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Re-Evaluation Committee, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - The Research Paper, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Steering Committee, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Student Teacher's Handbook, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - T.A. Materials, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Teaching Majors and Minors, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Syllabi, 1994-2008, Accession 2010-037; 6 cubic ft. (6 boxes); Additions of syllabi files dating from 1994 to 2008.
  - 1994-1997 (Box 1)
  - 1997-1999 (Box 2)
  - 2000-2002 (Box 3)
  - 2002-2004 (Box 4)
  - 2005-2006 (Box 5)
  - 2007-2008 (Box 6)